A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Auxiliary Services, Site Development FA849
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Auxiliary Services, Site Development
1916-1957
Rockefeller Archive Center
Cornell University. Medical College
Rockefeller University
New York University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Cornell University
FA849
4.8 Cubic Feet 4 boxes. Extent volume is appropriate.
4 boxes.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 880
Scope and Contents
Building blueprints; architectural drawings.
Biographical / Historical
Shepley, Rutan and Coolidge were the architects for the Central Laboratory (now called Founders) which was built on land purchased from the Schermer-horn Estate October 1902 plus an additional strip given to the Institute in 1904. The building was completed for occupancy May 11, 1906.
York and Sawyer were the architects for the Hospital and Isolation Pavilion. The formal opening was October 17, 1910.
Coolidge and Shattuck were the architects for the Middle Laboratory (now called Flexner) and new animal house and power house completed and occupied by 1916.
Coolidge and Shattuck were the architects for the Department of Animal Pathology buildings in Princeton, New Jersey which were completed in 1916.
Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott (changed from Coolidge and Shattuck July 1, 1924) were the architects for the library, assembly hall (now Welch Hall) and tunnel changes in New York City as well as the new laboratory and and animal building for the Department of Animal Pathology in Princeton which were opened 1928-1929.
Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott were the architects for the North Laboratory (now called Smith Hall), a low unit for combined laboratory and animal purposes, 1928-1930.
Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott submitted between 1930-1934 various plot plans and proposals for alterations.
Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott were the architects for the Plant Pathology buildings completed at Princeton in 1932.
James Mfg. Co. and Matthews Construction Co. were responsible for Dr. Wade Brown's laboratory completed at Princeton department in November 1935.
Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott were the architects and the builders were Vermilya -Brown Co. for the Plant Pathology buildings built 1947-1949 in New York City preparing for departmental move from Princeton.
Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott were the architects and Vermyla-Brown were the builders for the construction of a new wing and the modernization of the Hospital. Work was done between 1949-1951.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Due to the oversize nature and potentially brittle condition of the contents of this collection, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
Women; Medical education; Medicine, Preventive; Architecture; Medical sciences; Biology -- Research; Science -- Study and teaching; Life sciences; Women’s history; Medical research; Biochemistry; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Cornell University. Medical College; Rockefeller University; New York University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Cornell University
- Architectural history, 1916-1957
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the oversize nature and potential brittle condition of the contents of this collection, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
  - Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott building plans for Hospital. Designed and revised 1930-1934 for proposed additions and alterations (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes blueprints, floor by floor; compilations of floor potions; drawings of elevations and of exterior. Scheme "C" primarily.
  - Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott blueprints, 1931 (Box 2)
    1931 set of proposals for Hospital alterations and additions.
    Primarily Scheme "B".
  - Drawings of Plot Plans, 1930-1933 (Box 2)
    Various projections and including exterior designs and elevations. Includes drawings of proposed Hospital entrance (looking in and looking out).
  - Oversize map of Louvre Farm showing division into six parcels for inheritance and later divisions, 1868 December (Box 3)
    Indicates dwellings barns, cemetery and mansion.
  - Contour map of 64th-67th Streets inclusive of Rockefeller Institute grounds, 1903 May 1 (Box 3)
    Surveyed by Geo. C. Hollerith (?) for Shepley, Rutan and Coolidge.
  - Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott sketches and blueprints of suggestions for nurses' dining bay in the Hospital building, 1926 (Box 3)
  - Designs and drawings for Low Laboratory building and animal house, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Coolidge, Shepley, Bulfinch and Abbott sketches of elevations, and various designs primarily showing Exterior Street elevations. Drawings for new laboratory building and Hospital addition, 1929 (Box 3)
    Drawings of block plan #1, #2, #3
    Drawings of proposed waterfront changes.
  - Barth Equipment: Plans and budget for alterations to lunchroom kitchen, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Rockefeller University Master Plan - Alternate Study, re: air rights over FDR drive, 1973 September; 2 copies (Box 3)
  - Campus maps (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Cafeteria Alterations. 'B' Floor - Smith Hall. 6-27-58", Blueprint (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Received 18 September 1985 from Elizabeth Straight, Nursing.